A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Officers, RG 3 FA1797
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1931-2017; 1; 12.65 Cubic Feet 35 containers
  - Ibarguen, Alberto, 2006-2017; 1.8; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - Executive Committee Notes and Materials, 2014 April 11-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5324
      Notes and materials compiled by Lilly Weinberg, special assistant to Alberto, re: executive committee actions. Included is an agenda, discussion materials re: grant payout rates, KF communication metrics, memo re: prohibition on campaign intervention and lobbying (with revised version dated 9/7/14), Endowment process recommendation, Fluxx Grantee Portal feedback and survey results, and Contact & Relationship Management platform recommendation document.
    - Invitation to Earl Powell to join KF Board of Trustees; Memo to KF staff re: changes to senior manag, 2006 June 13-December 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3800
      Email from Alberto Ibarguen to Earl Powell to join the KF Board of Trustees immediately and Mr. Powell's affirmative response. Also included is a memo to KF staff about changes to the KF senior management team
    - Executive Committee Notes and Materials, 2015 January 5-2017 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5478
      Agendas for the monthly meetings of the Executive Committee. Also included is a report on 2014 media metrics by Andrew Sherry and a synopsis of the mid-year metrics for media coverage and digital communications for KF. A memo by Eric Newton re: Indirect cost policy and the schedule for the Media Learning Seminar #8 are included, as well as a memo from Sam Gill re: proposing a consistent approach to articulating strategy for each of Knight's four grant making programs.
      Restricted - Open in 2027
    - Transformation Fund Grants Since 2005, 2011 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5074
      Statistical informaton (pie charts, graphs, etc.) on the 208 grants awarded by KF from the Transformation Fund from 2005-2010. Also included is a detail chart of the grants listing organization, disposition, amount granted, project description, and program fund.
  - Knight, James L. and John S., 1931-2006; 1.9; 0.6 Cubic Feet 1 half-letter box and 1 oversize box
    James L. Knight, Co-founder, Chairman of the Board 1981-1991. One folder contains two letters outlining his hopes for the future of the Foundation (1987, 1990). The 1987 letter is hand-written.
    John S. Knight, Co-founder, President 1950-1975. Seventeen folders containing correspondence regarding the University of Missouri Freedom of Press Project (1958) and Mr. Knight's vision for the Foundation. Other topics include the possibility of keeping the Foundation in Akron after his death, contributions to KF by Knight newspapers, KF trustees, the Council on Foundations, KF holdings in Knight-Ridder newspaper stock, Ben Maidenburg and CC Gibson. Other folders include JS Knight's insurance policy, naming KF as beneficiary and his last will and testament. The remainder of John S. Knight's papers are located at the University of Akron Archives. SEE Record Group 11, Finding Aids for Related Collections, for a finding aid and inventory to his papers at the University of Akron.
    - Letter re: KF Move From Akron; Letter to Trustees Outlining Hopes for Future of Knight Foundation, 1987 September 1-1990 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 788
      Two letters: the first one (handwitten, it is a little difficult to decipher) to Knight Foundation trustee Henry King Stanford re: personal news and his thoughts on the likelihood of a Foundation move from Akron and the second to the Trustees in which he discusses his approval of the current policies on governance, finance and investments, payout, programs, grants and statement of purpose, and his hopes for the future of the Foundation.
    - The Editor's Notebook: by John S. Knight, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 5295
      Manuscript by Murray Powers re: John Knight's Editor's Notebook comments on the responsibilities of newspapermen. At one time, KF considered publishing the manuscript. Includes comments by Alberto Ibarguen and Eric Newton.
    - University of Missouri Freedom of the Press Project, 1958 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 789
      Correspondence between John S. Knight and Basil (Stuffy) Walters regarding Knight Foundation support for the University of Missouri freedom of the press project.
    - Correspondence re: Keeping the Foundation in Akron, 1979 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 982
      Letter from Norman Sugarman to John S. Knight in response to Knight's inquiry about legal means of keeping Knight Foundation in Akron after his death.
    - Contributions to the Knight Foundation, 1964 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 2654
      Letter from John S. Knight to Ben Maidenburg re: listing contributions to the Knight Foundation by the Miami Herald and Knight Publishing Company.
    - Memos, 1966 May 11-May 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 2655
      Memos re: agenda for Knight Foundation trustee meeting, new Foundation director, E.J. Thomas.
    - Memos, 1967 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 2656
      Memos to/from John S. Knight and Ben Maidenburg re: joining the Council on Foundations and stock options and the holdings of the Knight Foundation in Knight Newspapers, Inc.
    - Correspondence, 1969 November 3-7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 2658
      Correspondence between John S. Knight and EJ Thomas re: possible sale of Foundation holdings in Knight newspaper stock.
    - Correspondence, 1971 May 25-1972 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 2657
      Correspondence re: establishment of a committee of Knight Foundation trustees to consider the future direction of the Foundation and another committee to make recommendations to the Knight Foundation trustees with respect to journalism grant-making; interviews with candidates for Foundation director; and information on the Knight Foundation requested by Forbes magazine.
    - Correspondence, 1974 May 30-1975 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 2659
      Memos and correspondence re: desirability of producing an annual report; Ben Maidenburg's attendance at Council on Foundations meetings; and a policy statement, drafted by Lee Hills, outlining the procedures of how local newpaper managers should handle grant requests.
    - Correspondence, 1976 January 19-December 9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 2660
      Memos and correspondence re: renewing membership in the Council on Foundations, payout of grants, Ben Maidenburg's illness, and the hiring of CC Gibson to fill Maidenburg's job on a temporary basis.
    - Correspondence, 1977 January 3-October 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 2661
      Memos and correspondence re: CC Gibson's orientation to the directorship of the Foundation, acknowledgement of grants, Ben Maidenburg's health, and the annual report.
    - Correspondence, 1978 January 9-1979 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 2662
      Memos and correspondence re: description of Knight Foundation activities, including Knight's corrections to newspapers; Ben Maidenburg's retirement; and some newsclips on Knight Foundation.
    - Correspondence, 1980 February 29-1981 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 2663
      Memos and correspondence re: John S. Knight corrections to the minutes of the meeting of the Board of Trustees; CC Gibson activities; election of Barbara Knight Toomey and Gordon Heffern to the Board. In a letter dated March 26, 1981, Knight writes to CC Gibson that he has "caught" him in an error concerning Knight's birthplace.
    - Life Insurance Policy, 1931 March 23-1992 July 8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 2664
      Original life insurance policy of John S. Knight (dated 1931) naming his sons as beneficiaries. The beneficiary was changed in 1952 to The Knight Foundation. Two letters, dated 1992, respond to an inquiry from Tim Crowe, and state that the benefit had been paid out.
    - Last Will and Testament of John S. Knight, 1975 April 10-1996 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 2696
      Copy of the last will and testament of John S. Knight, 1975; a codicil, 1978; and a transmittal letter from a law firm to Jim Spaniolo enclosing the copy.
    - Quotable Quotes from Jack Knight, 1958-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 4654
      Eight quotes from speeches and writings of John S. Knight.
  - Maidenburg, Ben, 1945-1968; 1.10; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    Ben Maidenburg, Secretary and Manager 1958-1975, President 1976-1977. Thesenine folders document the earliest days of the Foundation's history (1945-1968). Mr. Maidenburg's nine folders contain information regarding the Knight Memorial Education Fund, its purpose, history and administration. An undated memo to the Board of Trustees discusses the fund, questioning whether the Foundation should give loans to students in cities whose newspapers do not contribute to the Foundation. Other issues include correspondence with John S. Knight regarding journalism scholarships at the University of Akron, scholarships for children of Akron Beacon Journal employees, and Foundation finances. Mr. Maidenburg's correspondence to recipients of the Knight Memorial Education Fund can be found in Record Group 10, Knight Memorial Education Fund, administrative and student files.
    - Memo to Trustees re: Student Loans (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 269
      Memo written to trustees (no date) re: background of the foundation's grants (all student loans) back to 1950, asks questions re: future of the student loan program (dollar limits, major areas of study, freshman only). Refers to C.L. Knight Memorial Education Fund.
    - Letter re: C.L. Knight Memorial Education Fund, 1945 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 270
      Letter to editor of Youngstown (OH) Vindicator re: history and statistics of C.L. Knight Memorial Education Fund and process by which student loans are awarded.
    - Correspondence re: Journalism Scholarships, 1952 December 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 271
      Letters from John S. Knight and Ben Maidenburg re: scholarship for journalism students.
    - Correspondence re: C.L. Knight Memorial Fund, 1957 September 10-11 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Knight File Number - 272
      Letters from Ben Maidenburg and John S. Knight re: change from C.L. Knight Memorial Fund to Knight Foundation.
    - Correspondence re: Scholarship Applications from Employees' Children, 1959 June 30-July 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Knight File Number - 273
      Letters between John S. Knight and Ben Maidenburg re: question of giving loans to children of employees of Knight Newspapers.
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1960 February 17-June 3 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Knight File Number - 274
      Letters between Ben Maidenburg and John S. Knight re: state of Knight Foundation finances, investments, and scholarships (student loans).
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1961 March 10-16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Knight File Number - 275
      Letters from Ben Maidenburg to John S. Knight asking for guidance in regard to Knight Foundation activities in 1961 (student loans, income and disbursements).
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1964 January 31-February 3 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Knight File Number - 276
      Correspondence between Ben Maidenburg and student loan recipient re: loan situation.
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1968 June 4-6 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Knight File Number - 277
      Correspondence between Ben Maidenburg and James L. Knight re: Knight Foundation funds, and grant applicants.
  - Maidenberg, Michael, 2001-2007; 1.11; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - Flight 93 Memorial, 2001 September 26-2006 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4657
      Correspondence, memos, newsletters and news releases re: planning for a memorial for the heroes of Flight 93, which crashed on September 11, 2001 in a field in Shanksville, PA after being hijacked by terrorists. The Foundation contributed $500,000 for the design competition and planning.
    - Correspondence Files, 2004 March 25-December 29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4658
      Routine correspondece and memos re: reorganization of Community Partners Program.
    - Correspondence Files, 2005 January 5-December 16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4660
      Routine correspondence.
    - Correspondence Files, 2006 January 4-December 15 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4661
      Routine correspondence. Includes two memos re: Grant Expenditure Evaluations.
    - Correspondence Files, 2007 January 5-November 9 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4662
    - Overtown Grant Analysis, 2007 June 8-July 17 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5073
      Detailed and critical review of Overtown (a low-income section of Miami) grants made by KF from 2000-2007. Also included is follow-up information on LISC Overtown grants.
    - Interviews with Community Partners Liaisons and KF Staff, 2005 January 19-February 14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4659
      Notes, and emails based on the interviews Mike did with KF staff to gather information on KF's work processes and areas in need of improvement.
  - Martinez, Juan, 2004-2007; 1.12; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - Anchor Point Capital, 2006 January 6-May 31 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4918
      Memoes and correspondence about/with Tim Crowe, former CFO of KF, about providing KF-related financial information to him.
    - ShoreBank Proposal, 2006 April 18-2007 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4920
      Correspondence, notes, and draft proposals submitted by ShoreBank, which approached KF for a grant (#20060181), for a loan package to be used to accelerate neighborhood transformation in Detroit by supporting equity-like developer investments in affordable housing and other real estate investments. The file outlines the shaping of the proposal until the grant was awarded.
    - American Ventures Property Fund, 2006 June 30-2007 March 7 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4921
      Financial statement, draft agreement, memos, and notes re: failure of American Venures Property Fund to comply with the terms of its agreement with KF.
    - Missed Vanguard 403(b) Payment, 2004 March 2-June 28 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4919
      Upon reconciling 2003 accounts, KF accounting staff discovered that the June 1, 2003 payment to Vanguard for 403(b) employee fund deductions hadn't been paid. The file spells out the problem and the solutions that were undertaken to make up the shortfall in employee accounts.
  - McPhee, Penelope, 1992-2000; 1.13; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - We Will Rebuild, 1992 December 1-1993 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4011
      Correspondence and minutes re: the Quality of Life Committee of We Will Rebuild, which was formed in the wake of Hurricane Andrew to guide the rebuilding process. Penny McPhee co-chaired the QOL committee, which was concerned with arts and cultural rebuilding. We Will Rebuild was chaired by Alvah Chapman.
    - General Correspondence, 1993-1997, 1993 December 27-1997 December 19 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4012
      Correspondence and memos re: grants, site visits, advisory committees, and other administrative matters.
    - Kids Voting USA, 1997 October 6-1998 March 16 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4013
      Correspondence and memos re: need to evaluate the Kids Voting USA program and getting feedback from advisors for their latest proposal. Also included are several research reports on the impact of the Kids Voting project prepared by independant evaluators.
    - General Correspondence, 1998 January 8-December 22 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
      Knight File Number - 4014
      Correspondence and memos re: grants, site visits, conferences, advisory committees, and other administrative matters. (Two folders.)
    - General Correspondence, 1999 February 7-November 17 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 4015
      Correspondence and memos re: grants, site visits, conferences, advisory committees, and other administrative matters.
    - General Correspondence, 2000, 2000 January 4-December 26 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 4016
  - Spaniolo, James, 1989-1996; 1.14; 0.57 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box and 1 half-letter document box
    James Spaniolo, Vice President and Chief Program Officer 1989-1996. Mr. Spaniolo's papers, 24 folders dating 1989-1996, indicate the Foundation's interest in literacy, as well as his participation in the Planning and Program Committee, and Finance Committee meetings. His files also contain notes from Board of Trustees and Advisor meetings, and information about legal issues regarding the incorporation of the Foundation in Ohio and Florida, and discussions of records management and strategic planning.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1992 September 23-December 22 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4009
      Two memos: streamlining of the grant-writeup process and the death of Akron employee Shirley Follo.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1993 January 8-October 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4010
      Includes summaries of grant data, changes in base guidelines for communities, and Hurricane Andrew grants.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1994 January 12-1994 July 29 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 3924
      Issues include donor-advised funding, grant inquiries, other Foundation policies and practices, and payments to advisory committee members.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1994 August 2-November 28 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 3925
      Issues include donor-advised funding, grant acknowledgement forms, grant inquiries, and meetings with grantees and trustees.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1995 January 26-December 21 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3926
      Issues include donor-advised funding, journalism focus group meetings, grant acknowledgement forms, grant inquiries, the use of The Magic of Music name, Kids Voting, strategic planning, the Minority Journalism Handbook and a Knight Chair at Yale University.
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1996 January 8-October 11 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 2490
      Issues include donor-advised funding, Kids Voting USA, Strategic Planning, Knight Chairs in Journalism, Minority Journalism Handbook, and grant deadlines.
    - Literacy, 1989 May 16-December 7 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 794
      Correspondence and proposal for Operation Read, from National Literacy Corporation.
    - Literacy, 1989 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 795
      Overview of evaluation approaches for KF funded literacy programs.
    - Legal Issues, 1990 January 16 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 796
      Correspondence regarding a Gannett Foundation ad which ties the foundation to one of its newspapers; discussion as to whether this is a good idea or not for Knight Foundation.
    - Legal Issues, 1990 May 7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 797
      Letter from Frank Harvey from Brouse & McDowell comparing the laws of Florida and Ohio with regard to incorporation.
    - Literacy, 1990 August 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 798
      Correspondence and background materials on APCO Associates, a consultant who worked with the UPS Foundation in the design and implementation of a grant initiative in the field of adult literacy. This material was sent to Jim Spaniolo for KF's interest in literacy projects.
    - Literacy, 1990 September 18 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 799
      Correspondence with KF regarding potential literacy project topics.
    - Literacy, 1990 July 26-1991 April 8 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 808
      Correspondence with APCO regarding updating a Knight Foundation report called "Illiteracy: the Silent Epidemic." Includes a draft of the report.
    - Literacy, 1991 January 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 807
      Jim Spaniolo's notes on Bronx Educational Services, regarding literacy.
    - Literacy, 1991 March 11 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 809
      Correspondence regarding the Mathematics Science Education Board and its interest in literacy.
    - Records Management Plan, 1990 August 2-October 31 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 800
      Correspondence regarding the implementation of a Records Management Plan by Ernst & Young, including a discussion of using Grants Manager as a new database system.
    - Records Management Plan, 1990 May 31 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 1006
      Report: "Profile of Existing Records," part 1 of 2 reports on a Records Management Plan by Ernst & Young. This report discusses the types of records produced by the foundation, and recommendations for storage, retention and disposition of the records.
    - Records Management Plan, 1990 August 9 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 1007
      Report: "Records Management Plan," part 2 of 2 reports on a Records Management Plan by Ernst & Young. This report discusses key findings and recommendations regarding file organization and retention, indexing and classification, space requirements, purging, file storage equipment, vital records protection program, microfilm policies and procedures, staffing for records management, operations manual, security and confidentiality, personnel records requirements, automated records management, and implementation plan.
    - Trustees Committees-Finance Committee, 1990 February 5-6 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 801
      Background materials for Finance Committee meeting of 3/19/90, including correspondence about a memorial for Dorothy Knight, and the Gannett Foundation offices.
    - Trustees Committees-Planning Committee, 1990 March 19 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 802
      Jim Spaniolo's meeting notes and the agenda for the Planning Committee meeting of 3/19/90. Topics include an Education Committee report, Cities Program bonus plan, Donor-Advised Funds Update, and a Literacy Consultant.
    - Trustees Committees-Planning Committee, 1990 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 803
      Jim Spaniolo's meeting notes and the agenda for the Planning Committee meeting of 6/19/90. Topics include a Journalism Advisory Committee report, Donor-Advised Funds Update, and a Literacy Update.
    - Trustees Meetings, 1990 March 20 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 804
      Jim Spaniolo's notes and background material for the Board of Trustees meeting of 3/20/90.
    - Trustees Meetings, 1990 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 805
      Jim Spaniolo's notes and background material for the Board of Trustees meeting of 6/19/90.
    - Trustees Meetings, 1996 March 19 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 813
      Jim Spaniolo's notes, agenda and meeting materials for Board of Trustees meeting of 3/19/96.
    - Trustees Meetings, 1996 September 17 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 814
      Jim Spaniolo's notes for Board of Trustees meeting of 9/17/96.
    - Grant Totals in Miami, 1991 April 29 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 806